Guide to the Wilfred Thomason Grenfell Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1855-1958, undated; Series XIV; 11.50 linear feet (28 boxes)
  - Wilfred T. Grenfell Family
    - Wilfred T. Grenfell, Jr.
      - Trip to Germany, 1934 summer (Box 58, Folder 316)
        Photograph No. 6848-6861
      - Dover College, England, 1935-1936 (Box 58, Folder 317)
        Photograph No. 6862-6877
      - MacJennet Camp, France, 1935-1937 (Box 58, Folder 318)
        Photograph No. 6878-6927
      - Tours of southern United States, 1940-1941 (Box 58, Folder 319)
        Photograph No. 6928-6971
      - Vermont, 1942 summer (Box 59, Folder 320)
        Photograph No. 6972-7041
      - Florida, 1942-1943 (Box 59, Folder 321)
        Photograph No. 7042-7079
      - St. Mark's School, 1942-1943 (Box 59, Folder 322)
        Photograph No. 7080-7122
    - Kinloch Pascoe Grenfell (Box 59, Folder 323)
      Photograph No. 7123-7139
    - Rosamond Loveday (Grenfell) Shaw and family (Box 59, Folder 324)
      Photograph No. 7140-7154, 8609. Photograph 8609 was previously unidentified and filed with unidentified photographs.
    - Family group pictures (Box 59, Folder 325-327)
      Photograph No. 7155-7315
    - Residences (Box 59, Folder 328)
      Photograph No. 7316-7360
    - Pets (Box 59, Folder 329)
      Photograph No. 7361-7387
  - Algernon Sydney Grenfell Family
    - Algernon Sydney Grenfell, father of Wilfred T. Grenfell (Box 60, Folder 330)
      Photograph No. 7388-7393
    - Jane Georgiana (Hutchinson) Grenfell, mother of Wilfred T. Grenfell (Box 60, Folder 331)
      Photograph No. 7394-7412
    - Algernon G. Grenfell, brother of Wilfred T. Grenfell, and family (Box 60, Folder 332)
      Photograph No. 7413-7443
    - Cecil Grenfell, brother of Wilfred T. Grenfell (Box 60, Folder 333)
      Photograph No. 7444-7449
    - Residences (Box 60, Folder 334)
      Photograph No. 7450-7490
  - Hutchinson Family
    - Portraits (Box 60, Folder 335)
      Photograph No. 7491-7507
  - Collateral Families
    - Grenfell family (Box 60, Folder 336)
      Photograph No. 7508-7512
    - Ponsonby family (Box 60, Folder 337)
      Photograph No. 7513-7516
    - Walker family (Box 60, Folder 338)
      Photograph No. 7517-7540
    - Unidentified families (Box 60, Folder 339)
      Photograph No. 7541-7552
  - MacClanahan Family
    - Portraits (Box 60, Folder 340)
      Photograph No. 7553-7599
    - Residences (Box 60, Folder 341)
      Photograph No. 7600-7705
  - Staff and Acquaintances
    - A-J (Box 61, Folder 342-350)
      Photograph No. 7706-7990
    - K-Su (Box 62, Folder 351-360)
      Photograph No. 7991-8286
      (for 8262) see: box 69, folder 3
    - T-Y (Box 63, Folder 361-363)
      Photograph No. 8287-8368
    - Unidentified (Box 63, Folder 364-367)
      Photograph No. 8369-8656
  - Grenfell Associations
    - Dog Team Tavern, Vermont (Box 63, Folder 368)
      Photograph No. 8657-8683
    - Industrial shop and goods (Box 63, Folder 369)
      Photograph No. 8684-8726
    - Miscellaneous (Box 64, Folder 370)
      Photograph No. 8727-8732
  - R.N.M.D.S.F. (Royal National Mission to Deep Sea Fishermen) (Box 64, Folder 371)
    Photograph No. 8733-8735
  - Scientific Projects
    - "Water Power Survey Behind St. Anthony's in the White Hills," 1921 (Box 64, Folder 372)
      Photograph No. 8736-8749
    - Cellulose acetate film experiments, 1938 (Box 64, Folder 373)
      Photograph No. 8750-8786
    - Nutrition experiments, n.d. (Box 64, Folder 374)
      Photograph No. 8787-8793
  - World Tours
    - Ireland, 1891 (Box 64, Folder 375)
      Photograph No. 8794-8875
    - "A Summer Holiday in France and Spain with Bicycles," 1898 Aug-Sep (Box 64, Folder 376)
      Photograph No. 8876-8927
    - Switzerland, [1898?] winter (Box 64, Folder 377)
      Photograph No. 8928-8973
    - Brussells, Germany, Switzerland, [ca. 1898-1899] (Box 64, Folder 378)
      Photograph No. 8974-9004
    - Spain, 1900 Dec-1901 Jan (Box 64, Folder 379)
      Photograph No. 9005-9026
    - "Motor Trip in France and Italy," 1907 [May?]-Jun (Box 64, Folder 380)
      Photograph No. 9027-9064
    - Italy and Greece, [ca. 1909-1912?] (Box 64, Folder 381)
      Photograph No. 9065-9077
    - [California and Western United States?], [1920?] (Box 64, Folder 382)
      Photograph No. 9078-9163
    - Asian tour, 1924 Nov-1925 May
      - Italy and Egypt (Box 65, Folder 383)
        Photograph No. 9164-9252
      - Egypt (Box 65, Folder 384)
        Photograph No. 9253-9344
      - Middle East (Box 65, Folder 385)
        Photograph No. 9345-9458
      - India (Box 65, Folder 386-387)
        Photograph No. 9459-9695
      - Indonesia (Box 65, Folder 388)
        Photograph No. 9696-9700
      - China (Box 66, Folder 389-391)
        Photograph No. 9701-10,014
      - Korea and Japan (Box 66, Folder 392)
        Photograph No. 10,015-10,080
    - Tour of Germany and Italy (Box 66, Folder 393)
      Photograph No. 10,081-10,149
    - Alassio, Italy, 1931-1932 winter (Box 66, Folder 394)
      Photograph No. 10,150-10,179
  - Places not in Newfoundland or Labrador
    - Austria (Box 66, Folder 395)
      Photograph No. 10,180-10,186
    - Canada (Box 66, Folder 396)
      Photograph No. 10,187-10,213
    - China (Box 66, Folder 397)
      Photograph No. 10,214-10,215
    - French North Africa (Box 67, Folder 398)
      Photograph No. 10,216-10,256
    - Great Britain (Box 67, Folder 399)
      Photograph No. 10,257-10,285
    - Greenland (Box 67, Folder 400)
      Photograph No. 10,286-10,288
    - Iceland (Box 67, Folder 401)
      Photograph No. 10,289
    - Italy (Box 67, Folder 402)
      Photograph No. 10,290
    - Palestine (Box 67, Folder 403)
      Photograph No. 10,291-10,292
    - Puerto Rico (Box 67, Folder 404)
      Photograph No. 10,293-10,294
    - Switzerland (Box 67, Folder 405)
      Photograph No. 10,295
    - Turkey (Box 67, Folder 406)
      Photograph No. 10,296
    - Uganda (Box 67, Folder 407)
      Photograph No. 10,297
    - United States of America (Box 67, Folder 408)
      Photograph No. 10,298-10,331
    - Unidentified locations (Box 67, Folder 409)
      Photograph No. 10,332-10,339
  - Miscellaneous (Box 67, Folder 410)
    Photograph No. 10,400-10,408, 10,489-10,491
  - Albums
    - Untitled photograph album with assorted photographs of Great Britain and Newfoundland, [ca. 1875-1900] (Box 67, Folder 410)
      See: box 69, folder 4
    - "Cruise of the Mission Hospital Smack 'Albert' to the coasts of Labrador and Newfoundland," 1892 (Box 68, Folder 411)
    - "Winter Life in Labrador," 1900 (Box 68, Folder 412)
    - Untitled photograph album with assorted photographs of Labrador and Newfoundland [ca. 1910-1920] (Box 68, Folder 413)
- OVERSIZE, 1884-1935, undated; Series XV; 1.25; (1 box)
  This series contains items which were too large to be filed in the regular sequence. Each item has been cross-referenced at the appropriate place in the folder list.
  - Legal papers and certificates, 1884-1902 (Box 69, Folder 1)
  - "Labrador Lithographs" by Valga Vaughan, 1935 May (Box 69, Folder 2)
  - Photograph of Isaac Sprague (#8262), 1931 (Box 69, Folder 3)
  - [Untitled photograph album with photographs of Great Britian and Newfoundland], [ca. 1875-1900] (Box 69, Folder 4)
- Additional Material, 1911-1940,1964, undated; Accession 1988-M-022; 0.25; (1 box)
  Addition inventory by Carol King 1989 Nov
  Received from: Janet G. Kahler, 1989 June'15
  - Correspondence
    - W. T. Grenfell to W. R. Stirling, 1911-1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - W. T. Grenfell to Dorothy Stirling, 1911-1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - W. T. Grenfell to Mrs. John Jamison, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Anne Grenfell, 1911, 1916, 1918, 1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Harriot Houghteling, 1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Grenfell Association of America, 1918, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Others and unidentified, 1911, 1922, 1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Writings
    - "The First Cruise of the George B. Cluett," by W. R. Stirling, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Labrador," by Harriot Houghteling, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Unidentified writings about W. T. Grenfell, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Articles and printed material, 1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1911, 1916, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Additional Material, 1903-1941, 1970s-1980s, undated; Accession 1991-M-022; 1.25 linear feet (3 boxes)
  Addition inventory by Carol King 1990 Oct
  Received from: Wilfred T. Grenfell, Jr., 1990 Sep 13
  - Correspondence and subject files
    - Grenfell, Anne, 1935 Dec, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Grenfell, Wilfred T.: biographical data, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Grenfell Labrador Medical Mission, important dates in history of (1892-1950), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
      See also: box 1,folder 13
    - Grenfell Labrador Medical Mission, minutes and endowments of, 1920-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      See also: box 1, folder 13
    - International Grenfell Association Board of Directors' minutes and correspondence, 1920-1929, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Petition presented to House of Assembly re: certain alleged operations of the International Grenfell Association, 1917 July 13 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Evidence Taken on the Grenfell Inquiry", 1917 September 11, 19-21 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Evidence Taken on the Grenfell Inquiry", 1917 September 24-October 29 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Reports on Charges Against Grenfell Association", 1917 November 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Livingston, Goodhue, 1978 July 13 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Mount, Harry, 1928 May 1- December 27, 1929 January 21- April 25, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - National Library of Canada, 1978 September 25 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Public Archives Canada, 1977 October 12-1978 February 17 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Religion and morality, 1977-1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Retirement and death of W.T. Grenfell, 1936 January 8, 1938 October 31, 1939-1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Rompkey, Ronald G., 1984, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Royal National Mission to Deep Sea Fishermen, 1979 August 7, 1980 March 6, June 9, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Sears, F.C., 1930-1931,undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Sears-Ferris, Pat, 1932-1933, 1942, 1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 18a)
    - Tamblyn-Brown report on the Mission (pages 92-93), 1938 February 4 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Wharmby, J.H. (Box 1, Folder 19)
      See: box 1, folder 20
    - "The Writer and His Books", 1909, 1913, 1934, 1938, 1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Writings by and about W.T. Grenfell
    - "The Legacy of Sir Wilfred Grenfell," by Calvin Coish, 1979 June (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "A Mower Ketch was Grenfell Mission's Intrepid Workhouse," by Roger C. Taylor, 1979 October (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - "Elements of Spiritual Autobiography in Sir Wilfred Grenfell's A Labrador Doctor, " by Ronald Rompkey, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - "The Viking Doctor of Labrador: My Most Unforgettable Character," by A.A. Chesterfield, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - "Among the Deep-Sea Fishers", 1903-1912 (Box 1, Folder 25-29)
      1903 Apr, Jul, Oct; 1904 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct, 1905 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct, 1906 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct; 1097 Jan, Apr, Oct, 1911 Jan, Apr, Jul, 1912 Jan, Apr, Oct
    - "Among the Deep-Sea Fishers", 1913-1934 (Box 2, Folder 30-40)
      1913 Jan, Apr, Jul; 1914 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct, 1915 Jan, Jul, Oct; 1916 Jan, Jul, Oct, 1917 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct; 1918 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct, 1919 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct; 1920 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct, 1921 Jan, Jul, Oct; 1922 Jan, Jul, Oct, 1923 Jan, Apr, Jul Oct; 1924 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct, 1925 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct; 1926 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct, 1927 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct; 1928 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct, 1929 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct; 1930 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct, 1931 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct; 1932 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct, 1933 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct; 1934 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct
    - "Among the Deep-Sea Fishers", 1935-1977 (Box 3, Folder 41-43)
      1935 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct; 1936 Jan, Oct; 1937 Jan, Jul, Oct, 1938 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct; 1939 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct; 1940 Jan, Apr, Jul, Oct; 1941 Jan, Oct; 1942 Jan, Apr, 1977 Oct, no date
    - "Toilers of the Deep", 1934 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Photographs, 1909, 1929, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings, 1903, 1906-1914, 1972. undated (Box 3, Folder 46-47)
  - Canadian Antiques Collector, special provincial issue featuring Newfoundland, 1975 March-April (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1931 May 17, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Photographs of the Wilfred Grenfell Mission Station Cartwright, Labrador, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    Originally part of Accession 1991-M-053
    Received from: Harry G. Toland, 1991 Jan 30
- Additional Material, 1924-1986, undated; Accession 1996-M-132
  Also includes Accession 1997-M-001
  - Correspondence
    - Ryerson, Knowles [professional colleague and personal friend of the Grenfell family]
      - Ba-Co (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Grenfell, Anne, 1929, 1935-1938, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Grenfell, Kinloch Pascoe, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Grenfell, Peter, 1970, 1977-1979, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Grenfell, Wilfred T.
        - 1924-1933 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - 1934-1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        - 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        - 1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Grenfell Association of America, 1928-1929, 1935-1942, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Grenfell Association of Great Britain and Ireland, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Grenfell Historical Society, 1979-1982, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Grenfell Labrador Industries, 1933-1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - International Grenfell Association, 1928, 1934, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - La-Mi (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Lady Grenfell Memorial Fund, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - New England Grenfell Association, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Ro-Vi (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Shaw, Rosamond (Grenfell), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Unidentified, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Shaw, Rosamond (Grenfell)
      - Curtis, Charles [successor to Wilfred T. Grenfell's Labrador work], 1959 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Subject files
    - Agriculture ["The Pageant of the Soil," a paper on lime burning, presumably prepared or sent to Wilfred T. Grenfell by Knowles Ryerson while at the Department of Agriculture], 1924 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Benedictions, prayers by Wilfred T. Grenfell, 1940, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Bibliography of Wilfred T. Grenfell's writings, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Clippings on Wilfred T. Grenfell's Labrador missions, 1933, 1942, 1981, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Dogteam Tea Houses [located in Connecticut and Vermont and operated by Grenfell Labrador Industries], 1936-1937, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Grenfell Associations, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Grenfell Juniors, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Itinerary of tour of the United States, 1929 Feb 1-26 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Labrador Cruises, 1934, 1936, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Memorial service, obituary of Wilfred T. Grenfell, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Needlework Guild of America, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Postcards/greeting cards, blank [fund raisers for Labrador mission work], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - University of California, College of Agriculture [program from Charter Day Anniversary Ceremony at which Wilfred T. Grenfell gave the invocation; Knowles Ryerson was Assistant Dean], 1940 Mar 27 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Photographs
    - Grenfell, Wilfred T., 1933, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Grenfell family members, 1951, 1953, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Labrador scenes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Ryerson, Knowles, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Reproductions
    - Calendars [fund raisers depicting Wilfred T. Grenfell on board Strathcona], 1932-1936 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Physician's Window, Washington Cathedral [stained glass window depicting Wilfred T. Grenfell in Labrador clothing], 1947 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Strathcona> [album of scenes depicting Wilfred T. Grenfell's missions in Labrador; Accession 1997-M-001], n.d. (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Sketch
    - Peary, Robert [ink sketch by Wilfred T. Grenfell with inscription: "A sketch I sent and made for Mother of our friend Comr Peary who conquered the North Pole"], n.d. (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Additional Material, Accession 1991-M-023
  - Correspondence
    - Ashdown, Cecil, 1926-1930, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ashdown, David, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Richards, Henry, 1948 Jan 29 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1932, 1935, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Printed material, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs
    - Family, mission sites [identified and unidentified], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Album [also contains sketches pertaining to New Foundland], 1911, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 6)